In this video, we will again look
at a few formal aspects of Petri nets.
Reminder:
We had formally defined Petri nets
as a tuple containing a set
of places S and a set
of transitions T, plus various other ingredients.
Among them were markings, i.e. functions from the
set of places S into the natural numbers.
No negative numbers, but
zero and positive integers.
That was used, among other things,
to express the pre- and postweights.
These were
these special functions.
For individual transitions, respectively
the precondition weights and the
postcondition weights
as such markings.
The connection to the graphical representation
was, first, that the initial marking m0
corresponded to the occupancy of the places
at the beginning on the graphical page.
Since, the marking function m0
would be used to count
exactly the tokens for each
place shown in the graphical representation.
And the arrows in
the graphical representation correspond
exactly to the pre and
post weights in a certain way.
In particular, if there is to be no arrow from s
to t or from t to s (in each case in the
appropriate order), that from it can
be read whether the pre-weight condition function
for that transition carries the value
zero with respect to the corresponding place.
Or analogously for
the post-weight function:
If there are zeros
in the mathematical representation, there
is simply no arrow
in the graphical representation.
Then there was the situation that there was
an arrow, but there was nothing on it.
This would
correspond to the
cases where the pre-weight and post-weight functions
for the corresponding transition and place are 1.
Differently, we had
seen in the tool
that there the arrows are
always labeled with a 1.
So even with the arrows that
would carry a 1 and therefore in
the simplified graphical representation
in the slides, for example,
are not labeled with a number, the
1 was still explicitly there in the tool.
On the slides, I actually write the
weights only if they are greater than 1.
So if the
pre-weight and post-weight
condition for a transition and
place is an integer greater than
1, then there would be an arrow
on the slides or in the exercises.
If there is nothing on
it, then it is a 1.
And in the tool, the
1 is even written on it.
That's just
a repetition.
This is nothing new
that I told you.
You've already seen that
and you've also practiced that.
Then now we're going to operate
with these "ingredients," specifically these markings.
We're going to have a couple
of terms and a couple of definitions
that are defined for markings and because
of that, they then apply to the initial
marking as well as they can be
used for these pre-weight and post-weight functions.
And also for other markings that arise in
the course of the development of a Petri net.
So not just the
initial marking, but also markings
that may be present, for example,
after some transitions have been executed.
And then we just need
some mathematical terms and applications.
So on the one hand,
there will be an order
on markings, and on
the other hand, certain operations.
On this slide, first
of all, to the order.
We'll consider any two
markings for the same
Petri net, so for
the same set of places.
Then we have two markings, that is,
mappings from these places to natural numbers.
I'll call them
m and m'.
The m' has nothing
to do with derivatives.
It's not somehow the differential
calculus stroke: f and f'.
They are just
two different names.
You could have
also said m1, m2.
And then how is it defined
that m' is less than-equal to m?
If it is true
for all places from the
corresponding underlying set that m' of s is
less than or equal to m of s.
So, that at the place
s the marking m' carries a
smaller value or the same value
as m at the corresponding place.
And this must be
true for all places.
Then we say that the marking m'
is altogether less-than-equal to the marking m.
That's not about what the sum
of the numbers for the marking is.
How many tokens
there are in total.
Instead, it must
be true for each
token that m' carries a smaller value
or at most the same value as m.
Then we also say:
m' is covered by m.
Finally, we check that m has at least
as many tokens as m' for each place.
So, does
m overlap m'?
Example:
Suppose our set of
places S is three-elementary.
We have already said that we can
write down such finite functions by simply
specifying (in that case) a triple, because
there are supposed to be three places.
Then our m could
be the triple (0,1,2).
And m', of course seen for the
same order of places, the triple (0,0,1).
And then it would indeed hold here that
m' is less-equal to m, but not vice versa.
Why is
m' <= m?
Because 0 is less than or equal to 0, and 0 is less
than or equal to 1, and 1 is less than or equal to 2.
But the reverse
is not true.
The 0 <= 0 is still
true, but not 1 <= 0.
In that case, we would say
that marking is covered by this marking.
It really depends on
the comparison of each element.
Also, this
is still true:
Every marking is
covered by itself, trivially,
because it is less-equal,
namely equal, at every position.
But what is not true
is for example this one.
So although the second marking here
is much fuller in a place
(1000), which is much larger
than everything in the first marking.
Nevertheless, this marking is
not covered by this one.
Why
not?
Because it is not
true in the third place.
But it would have to be
true for every place that the
number, which stands here is smaller-equal
to the number, which stands there.
This is the case for 3 and 5
and for 1000, but not for 2 and 1.
Sometimes it is simply not
the case that the overlap exists.
And it may also be that
it is not present in either direction.
That was already the case
here, and indeed also here.
Although here in both markings simply the numbers 0,
1, 2 occur, it is neither the case that
the first marking is covered
by the second, nor vice versa.
Because there is in each case a place,
namely either the second or the third position,
where in each case it is
violated that this applies to all places.
So this is how we can compare
two markings, be it the initial marking
and a weight
marking, or two weight
markings, or just two markings that occur
later in the development of the Petri net.
We'll write this "<=", which is what
you're most likely to know for numbers.
Mathematicians like to use
this for all sorts of
structures, including such
marking functions, for example.
Then it said
something about operations.
This is just an
order relation, not an operation.
So nothing that
creates a new marking.
But there are some
of these, especially the addition.
So if we have
again two such markings, for
the same set of places, then we
define a third marking, which is the sum.
Now here's this somewhat funny
plus with a circle around it.
That's simply choosing a symbol
that's not the obvious plus (which
you know from numbers), but
still reminds you of addition.
That's where people like to
take symbols of about that shape.
So a plus in a circle,
because it's not the plus on numbers.
Not 3 + 5, but
the plus between two such markings.
What comes
out of it?
A marking, which must be a
function of S into the natural numbers.
And how
is it defined?
Well,
in places.
So for each element of S, we
define our new marking as given at that
place, by the sum of the
two original markings at the same place.
That's simply
a definition.
So for each s,
we define a natural number.
And then that is the
result marking of that addition.
For example, if again for the
three-element set S we have the markings
(0,1,2) and (0,0,1), then their
sum would again be a
marking for this three-element
place set, therefore a triple.
And that is 0 + 0 = 0, 1
+ 0 = 1, and 2 + 1 = 3.
So this is
like vector addition.
If you were to
write things down vertically,
that would be a triple
vector and another triple vector.
You know this from
school (linear algebra), there
just comes out
a vector, element-wise/place-wise added.
Exactly the same
happens for these markings.
You can do
that for addition.
the same for subtraction.
Then you just have
to be a little careful,
because it says here that it
always has to be natural numbers.
And it's unfortunately not
the case that when you
subtract any two natural numbers, the
result is always a natural number.
For example with 3 and 5 this is not the case, 3
+ 5 = 8 but 3 - 5 is not a natural number.
Therefore, subtraction is defined
only for the case where
we want to subtract from m
a marking that is covered by m.
Here we use the relation,
the order, from the slide before.
So if m' <=
m, as defined before,
then we can say the subtraction of
m and m' is in that order:
For each place, it must hold that
the new marking at the place no
longer carries as its value the sum,
but the difference, of the two original sets.
The order is
of course important.
That we subtract m' from m and
not vice versa. Here it is okay.
There will actually
come out a natural
number, if we knew before
that m' is covered by m.
Because then it is exactly the case
that this difference can never be negative.
So that will
then fit exactly.
Again, an example: (0,1,2)
minus (0,0,1) would be (0,1,1).
So don't add element by
element, but subtract element by element.
We may not turn this around
here; here above of course already.
Here above for the sum
we could have also written:
What is written here as second
plus what is written here as first.
This is also defined and results in
the same triple, because this addition is commutative.
That does not apply
here for the subtraction,
because this condition would not be
fulfilled then for the other direction.
Then we can
use these terms now.
These were only definitions of
mathematical kind for these markings.
This has nothing to
do with Petri nets.
But we just want
to use that to describe
the dynamics, the semantics, the meaning
(ultimately the execution) of Petri nets.
What was
important there?
Being
activated.
Is a transition in
a Petri net activated?
Only then
can anything happen.
And what
happens then?
The transition fires and leads
to a new marking, to a
new allocation of the
places in the Petri net.
We can now formally define these two
concepts using the terms we have seen.
So first
the activation.
When is a transition
activated for a particular marking?
So we have to have a marking,
we have to know where the tokens are.
And then we can look
at a transition and ask
if that transition is activated
right now for the current marking.
That's the case when
the pre-weight function for that
particular transition is covered
by the current marking.
This means exactly that at all
places where this transition expects tokens, i.e.
where the function value of
this function is greater than
0, the marking m also contains at
least as many tokens (or maybe even more).
This must be
true for every place.
A transition can
already not fire if
there are not enough tokens in the
current marking for one of its input places.
What is written here in the
parentheses is simply the verbalization of what
the definition of the order relation
of the penultimate slide provides here.
So it succinctly captures
when a transition is activated.
And when it
is, it can fire.
So, let t be a transition and m be
a marking such that t is activated for m.
Then it
can fire.
This means that a
new marking comes out.
And what does
it look like?
We can now rewrite
it with our subtraction/addition.
Intuitively we
had said:
We take correspondingly
many tokens from all
places of the precondition, that
is, with incoming arrows to t.
Where "correspondingly many"
depends on what this
function says here
for the individual places.
And on the other hand, afterwards
we add suitably many tokens to the
post-weight places, that is, to the places for
which this post-weight function has a positive value.
This is exactly
the same as saying:
We take the current
marking, subtract from it the
pre-weight function for the corresponding t, and
add the post-weight function on top of it.
After all, this is the same transition in each
case, and it is the one we are firing.
And we must know beforehand that t
is really activated for this marking m.
Because only then we
can form this subtraction.
So this all fits together with the
condition in the previous slide about when we're
allowed to form the
subtraction in the first place.
Things play together exactly so
that it makes sense overall.
What's meant by
the parentheses here is:
First we subtract
and then we add.
You could have
added parentheses there.
If that is so, then we also want to
express more concisely: m becomes m' when t is fired.
And that is
how it is written.
This is a syntax
formulated as a formula
for: t now fires from here
to there and out comes m'.
And this is exactly the m'
which results from these arithmetic operations.
That would
be a step.
So from a marking we
make a step with a certain
transition and get a
certain new marking m'.
That could happen to
be the same one.
But generally
some marking m'.
Then obviously m' is reachable
in a step of m.
This can still be generalized
or taken in a different way.
Namely, one can
ask whether some marking,
not necessarily m', but some
other marking, is reachable from m.
Perhaps also
in several steps.
This gives
our next definition.
We say a marking
is reachable, usually from m0.
So we have a start
marking for the Petri net.
We wonder if some other
marking is reachable from it.
How is this defined and
when is it the case?
When there is a
certain sequence of transitions.
This could be a single transition, it
could be zero, it could be 27,
but somehow a finite
sequence t_1 to t_n.
In that, transitions may
occur more than once.
So maybe our Petri
net has three transitions,
but we want to
have a 27 long sequence.
Then at least one transition
must occur more than once.
So any transitions t_1 to t_n,
possibly occurring more than once, so
that m0 becomes m1 by firing t1, exactly this m1
becomes m3 by firing t2, and so on, and so on.
And in the end, our m comes out,
which we wondered if it is reachable from m0.
And if it is, then m
is called reachable from the initial marking.
Sometimes we don't even care
what these intermediate markings are.
Then we only want to know that we can
get from m0 to m by t_1 to t_n.
Then this is also written shortened as:
just m0, then all transitions are written here
directly in these special
brackets (not each one separately),
and we write only the end
token there (not also all intermediate markings).
Or if we summarized this list
t_1 to t_n, as here t-"snake", so
another identifier; then we also write, m0
passes into m under this whole sequence.
The sequence is then
called a firing sequence.
These are exactly the lists that show up
in the tool in the previous video in
the left window, but
written one below the other.
I had single transitions
in my Petri nets.
There I simulated, started
executions and carried out circuits,
and in the left window the
transitions always appeared under each other.
That would be
such a firing sequence.
At the beginning
it was empty.
One can also have
the empty firing sequence.
Then, of course, the m
is necessarily equal to the m0.
Each marking, also
the initial marking
m0, passes under empty
firing sequence naturally into itself.
One can also have the situation that
there is only the empty firing sequence.
If I have no activated transitions at all
in the initial marking of the Petri net,
then the only possible firing
sequence is the empty firing sequence.
But in general, it will
be the case that we will
have finite and non-empty
transition sequences that are fireable.
Then we have
an interesting model.
That was
the definition.
Let's talk through this
with a concrete example.
This is the example I had
on a slide last week where we
were talking about the equivalence
of graphical and mathematical representation.
So there is a slide,
in last week's slides, where
the mathematical representation
is given for this.
We need that here now as
well, because these terms refer to that,
especially these
marking functions.
Here we have the initial marking, that
would be as marking m0 of course
(1,2,0) because I have the
place order s1, s2, s3.
So the initial marking
here would be: first component
1, second component
2, third component 0.
Now it is claimed here that the marking
m2 = (1,1,1) is reachable in two steps.
Intuitively, this means it
must be possible to
perform exactly two
circuits/firings of transitions so
that somehow the tokens move in such a way
that afterwards there is exactly one token on each position.
That's what this
marking here says.
And we can just try
that out and do the math.
We can see that of these three transitions,
only t1 is activated at the beginning anyway.
Therefore, the first circuit really
has to happen with t1.
The pre-weight function for t1 is (1,1,0), because
there must be something on the first two places.
There are incoming arrows, and
without a number written on them,
so this corresponds
to weight 1.
There is no incoming arrow from
s3 to t1, so this is zero.
That's what it had said
on the slide last week.
This marking is covered
by the start marking.
The m0 in this
case would be (1,2,0).
There this relation is valid,
because at every position the value,
which is here, is at least
as high as the value here.
So firing is possible
in the first place.
Of course we already knew
this by looking at this
graphic, but mathematically
this is well defined.
What do
we get then?
The next marking
is our start marking
m0 minus the pre-weight function for
t1, plus the post-weight function for t1.
There we could also look at the old
slides and it would say that this is (0,0,2).
Ultimately because there are no arrows from t1 to s1
and s2, but there is this 2 arrow to s3.
So we
have this calculation:
We have (1,2,0) as
m0, minus (1,1,0), plus (0,0,2).
Then calculating element by
element we get (0,1,2).
1 - 1 + 0 = 0, 2 - 1 +
0 = 1, and 0 - 0 + 2 = 2.
So the marking m1 after firing t1
in the start situation is this marking.
Now if we want to
know what happens in two steps,
we have to make the next step
starting from this, not from m0 anymore.
We can see, this current marking
(0,1,2) covers the pre-weight of t2.
The pre-weight function of t2 is (0,0,1)
because it only takes something from s3.
This (0,0,1) is covered by
it, so t2 is executable.
Then m2 is the current marking
m1 minus exactly this (0,0,1), so it
is the pre-weight function of t2,
plus the post-weight function of t2.
If we look
there what happens:
t2 puts a token after s1 and
nothing else, so the function is (1,0,0).
As a calculation, we get from
up here: (0,1,2) - (0,0,1) + (1,0,0).
And if we do this again element
by element, we get the marking (1,1,1).
So after firing t1 and t2, from
the original marking, we would reach the
situation as it is claimed here above, where
on all three places there is exactly one token.
So it is valid: m0 under
firing of t1 passes to this
m1, and under firing of
t2 this passes to this m2.
Or written shorter (if we don't
want to note the m1 at
all): m0 passes to m2
under firing of t1 and t2.
Calculated
this way.
Of course, we will not
always recalculate this in such detail.
But it
must be understood,
because later definitions will
work with these terms.
Often, we will certainly
just work with intuition, based
on the
graphical representation.
That's what I did in the
modeling example in the previous video.
I didn't always
do the math, but
simply worked with the tool
and the intuition behind it.
It is still important that this is
now simply the firing for this concrete sequence.
So it's not that m0 always
does this and then m2 comes out.
But here it only says
that m0 can change into this
concrete marking m2 by
firing t1 and t2.
There can also be other
firing sequences starting from m0.
In the concrete case for example
it is also valid that m0 reaches
m1 after firing t1 as above, but
after that also t3 would have been fireable.
So a different
transition than t2.
And then a completely different
final marking would have come out.
This is not
a contradiction or wrong.
But the firing always refers
to a concrete sequence of transitions.
For other transitions of course
another marking can come out.
This follows mathematically
from the definition.
But this is also an essential
property of Petri nets, namely non-determinism.
That is, it is possible, in the
same situation, for example situation m1 (which
we have reached here), to
evolve differently for different transitions.
The term for
this is "non-determinism".
Petri nets are
non-deterministic, not predetermined.
That is, there can be multiple
direct successor markings to a concrete marking.
Of course, there can
always be several successor markings,
since we are
considering several steps.
But even for the next concrete
step there can be different results.
Of course only if
we apply different transitions.
So the same marking
and the same transition lead
to the
same successor marking.
We can't get different
markings from m1 with t1.
But here with m1 and t2 or
m1 and t3 we get different markings.
If we have a
marking, and we can choose
different transitions, we can get
different new markings in the process.
Now at this point, from the
student side, the question likes to come:
Who
decides that?
Who chooses
the transition?
Or who chooses which of the
several successor markings is the right one?
For modeling, this
question does not arise.
That is not
our goal in modeling.
In modeling, we want
to describe all possibilities.
Nowhere in the Petri net does
it say which transition to take.
The Petri net describes, under a
certain constellation, which transitions are possible.
And also expresses what
this does to the marking.
What the next marking would
be for a chosen transition.
The model does not make a
selection of which transition to take.
That might be a
task for implementing a system
previously modeled
with Petri nets.
Perhaps one wants to
follow certain protocols in a
concrete
executable system.
So choosing certain strategies among all
the possibilities given by the model.
But that is no
longer part of the modeling.
This is
an important concept.
Without non-determinism, Petri nets
would not be as interesting.
And because Petri nets are
nondeterministic (i.e., different subsequent markings can
arise from one
marking), if we
want to get an overview of how a
Petri net can evolve, there is a very
natural relationship to the flat state
diagrams from the beginning of the lecture.
We will turn to
the evolution of a graph
from a Petri net, corresponding to
reachability relations, in the next video.